Guide to the Gillingham-Stith family papers, 1836-1932
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Gillingham-Stith family papers 1836-1932
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Gillingham-Stith family.
4.5 Linear Feet Approx. 4,074 Items
Mine owners and speculators residing in Cid and Thomasville (Davidson County), North Carolina.
Collection consist chiefly of correspondence, along with wills, deeds, and other personal, business, and legal papers of Mrs. Alberta Stith Jones Gillingham and of her brother, Fred H. Stith, mining speculator, of Cid and Thomasville (Davidson County), North Carolina. Most of the papers are Mrs. Gillingham's and center around the operation of gold, silver, copper, sulphur, and zinc mines in the Cid district of Davidson County, North Carolina, and the complications caused in family relationships because of contested inheritances and property rights. Alberta Gillingham was also a music composer, writer, and teacher; one of her compositions, "General Harrison's inaugural quick-step," was transferred to the post-bellum sheet music collection. Includes materials concerning Furnifold Simmon's campaign for U.S. Senate in 1930, letters from Stith's children in Trinity College (now Duke University), and correspondence between Mrs. Gillingham and William H. Bailey, a lawyer of Charlotte, North Carolina.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Gillingham-Stith family papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 1935 to 1960.
Biographical and Historical Note
Alberta Bassett (Stith Jones Gillingham was the daughter of Dr. Nicholas Long Bolling Stith, who graduated in medicine from the University of Pennsylvania in 1829 and who lived in Halifax County and then in Raleigh. He had at least two other children, Anna Guion and Fred H. Stith. Dr. Stith and his brother, A.B. Stith, bought 1000 shares of stock in the Ward gold mine in 1854, one of the largest mines in the Cid mining district of Davidson County, N.C. Mrs. Gillingham inherited at least part of the properties which she came to hold in the Cid mining district. It appears from the papers that her mining interests included gold, silver, copper, sulphur, and zinc. One of the mines she came to own was the Ward mine. Her first marriage in 1881 was to J. Howard Jones, also a mine owner, who died in 1884. She also became involved with a lawyer from Charlotte, William H. Bailey. She married her second husband, Captain H.R. Gillingham, in 1905. By then, Alberta and her brother and sister had become estranged, and a long legal battle ensued during the late 19th and early 20th centuries over the ownership of the mines.
Collection Overview
Collection consist chiefly of correspondence, along with wills, deeds, and other personal, business, and legal papers of Mrs. Alberta Stith Jones Gillingham and of her brother, Fred H. Stith, mining speculator, of Cid and Thomasville (Davidson County), North Carolina. Most of the papers are Mrs. Gillingham's and center around the operation of gold, silver, copper, sulphur, and zinc mines in the Cid district of Davidson County, North Carolina, and the complications caused in family relationships because of contested inheritances and property rights. Alberta Gillingham was also a music composer, writer, and teacher; one of her compositions, "General Harrison's inaugural quick-step," was transferred to the post-bellum sheet music collection. Includes materials concerning Furnifold Simmon's campaign for U.S. Senate in 1930, letters from Stith's children in Trinity College (now Duke University), and correspondence between Mrs. Gillingham and William H. Bailey, a lawyer of Charlotte, North Carolina.
Related Material
Music score book (F:6424), Anna P. Stith, Thomasville (Davidson County), N.C., undated
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Bailey, William H.
Gillingham, Alberta B. Stith Jones
Gillingham family
Stith, Fred H.
Stith family
Duke University -- History
Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.) -- Students
Gold mines and mining -- North Carolina
Industries -- North Carolina
Davidson County (N.C.) -- History
Contents of Collection
- Gillingham-Stith family papers, 1864-1932, (9 boxes)
  - Letters, 1846-1883, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1884-1886, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Letters, 1887-1889, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Letters, 1890-1898, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Letters, 1899-1909, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Letters, 1910-1924, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Letters, 1925-1932, (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - Letters, undated, (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - Bills and receipts, 1849-1931, (3 folders) (Box 9)
  - A.B. Stith receipt book, 1836-1866 (Box 9)
  - Ward Gold Mine Company minute book, 1854-1869 (Box 9)